<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml><records><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Pawłowska, Joanna</author><author>Angeles, Inés Andrea Barrenechea</author><author>Grzelak, Katarzyna</author><author>Deja, Kajetan</author><author>Zaborska, Agata</author><author>Pawłowski, Jan</author><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sediment DNA metabarcoding and morphology provide complementary insight into macrofauna and meiobenthos response to environmental gradients in an Arctic glacial fjord</title><secondary-title>Marine Environmental Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine Environmental Research</full-title></periodical><pages>106552</pages><volume>198</volume><keywords><keyword>Community Ecology</keyword><keyword>Environmental clines</keyword><keyword>Environmental DNA</keyword><keyword>Foraminifera</keyword><keyword>Macrobenthos</keyword><keyword>Meiofauna</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>0141-1136</isbn><electronic-resource-num>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marenvres.2024.106552</electronic-resource-num><abstract>ABSTRACT Arctic fjords ecosystems are highly dynamic, with organisms exposed to various natural stressors along with productivity clines driven by advection of water masses from shelves. The benthic response to these environmental clines has been extensively studied using traditional, morphology-based approaches mostly focusing on macroinvertebrates. In this study we analyse the effects of glacially mediated disturbance on the biodiversity of benthic macrofauna and meiobenthos (meiofauna and Foraminifera) in a Svalbard fjord by comparing morphology and eDNA metabarcoding. Three genetic markers targeting metazoans (COI), meiofauna (18S V1V2) and Foraminifera (18S 37f) were analysed. Univariate measures of alpha diversity and multivariate compositional dissimilarities were calculated and tested for similarities in response to environmental gradients using correlation analysis. Our study showed different taxonomic composition of morphological and molecular datasets for both macrofauna and meiobenthos. Some taxonomic groups while abundant in metabarcoding data were almost absent in morphology-based inventory and vice versa. In general, species richness and diversity measures in macrofauna morphological data were higher than in metabarcoding, and similar for the meiofauna. Both methodological approaches showed different patterns of response to the glacially mediated disturbance for the macrofauna and the meiobenthos. Macrofauna showed an evident distinction in taxonomic composition and a dramatic cline in alpha diversity indices between the outer and inner parts of fjord, while the meiobenthos showed a gradual change and more subtle responses to environmental changes along the fjord axis. The two methods can be seen as complementing rather than replacing each other. Morphological approach provides more accurate inventory of larger size species and more reliable quantitative data, while metabarcoding allows identification of inconspicuous taxa that are overlooked in morphology-based studies. As different taxa may show different sensitivities to environmental changes, both methods shall be used to monitor marine biodiversity in Arctic ecosystems and its response to dramatically changing environmental conditions.</abstract><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0141113624002137</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Kadac-Czapska, Kornelia</author><author>Jutrzenka Trzebiatowska, Patrycja</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Kowalczyk, Piotr</author><author>Knez, Eliza</author><author>Behrendt, Mirosław</author><author>Mahlik, Sebastian</author><author>Zaleska-Medynska, Adriana</author><author>Grembecka, Małgorzata</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Isolation and identification of microplastics in infant formulas – A potential health risk for children</title><secondary-title>Food Chemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Food Chemistry</full-title><abbr-1>Food Chemistry</abbr-1></periodical><pages>138246</pages><volume>440</volume><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>05/2024</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>03088146</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.138246</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Microplastics (MPs) are plastic particles between 0.1 and 5,000 µm in size that can contaminate food. Unfor­ tunately, to date, little attention has been paid to analyzing the presence of such particles in baby foods. The present study aimed to determine the degree of contamination of infant formula with MPs. A total of thirty products were subjected to analysis. The research methodology used included the isolation of plastic particles, identification and characterization of MPs using advanced microscopic and spectroscopic techniques. Micro­ plastics were detected in all tested samples. The most frequently identified polymers were polyamide, poly­ ethylene, polypropylene, and poly(ethylene terephthalate). The particles exhibited diverse forms, including fibers, fragments, and films, displaying a range of colors such as colorless, black, and brown particles. Furthermore, the daily intake of MPs by children fed exclusively infant formula was estimated to be approxi­ mately 49 ± 32 MPs. This poses a potential health risk for the youngest.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0308814623028649</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\YP2QQURT\Kadac-Czapska et al. - 2024 - Isolation and identification of microplastics in i.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:44:52</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ferrero, Luca</author><author>Scibetta, Lorenzo</author><author>Markuszewski, Piotr</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikolaj</author><author>Drozdowska, Violetta</author><author>Makuch, Przemysław</author><author>Jutrzenka-Trzebiatowska, Patrycja</author><author>Zaleska-Medynska, Adriana</author><author>Andò, Sergio</author><author>Saliu, Francesco</author><author>Nilsson, E. Douglas</author><author>Bolzacchini, E.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Airborne and marine microplastics from an oceanographic survey at the Baltic Sea: An emerging role of air-sea interaction?</title><secondary-title>Science of The Total Environment</secondary-title><short-title>Airborne and marine microplastics from an oceanographic survey at the Baltic Sea</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science of The Total Environment</full-title><abbr-1>Science of The Total Environment</abbr-1></periodical><pages>153709</pages><volume>824</volume><dates><year>2022</year><pub-dates><date>06/2022</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>00489697</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.153709</electronic-resource-num><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0048969722008014</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\PKJU2AJS\Ferrero et al. - 2022 - Airborne and marine microplastics from an oceanogr.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:41:43</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Górska, Barbara</author><author>Renaud, Paul E.</author><author>Legeżyńska, Joanna</author><author>Berge, Jørgen</author><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Seasonal constancy (summer vs. winter) of benthic size spectra in an Arctic fjord</title><secondary-title>Polar Biology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Polar Biology</full-title><abbr-1>Polar Biol</abbr-1></periodical><pages>1255-1270</pages><volume>42</volume><number>7</number><issue>7</issue><dates><year>2019</year><pub-dates><date>7/2019</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>0722-4060, 1432-2056</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s00300-019-02515-2</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Size spectra are important descriptors of community structure and can indicate changes in community functioning in response to shifts in environmental conditions. There are relatively few assessments of benthic size spectra, and most are based on summer samples alone. Processes influencing size spectra, such as recruitment and predation pressure, vary seasonally, and understanding this variation is necessary to interpret patterns in time or space. Here we compare summer and winter biomass size spectra in the central basin of Kongsfjorden (west Spitsbergen). We recorded seasonal changes in the quality of organic matter available to the benthos, indicated by higher chloroplastic pigments concentrations in surface sediments in summer, as well as in differences in total abundance and biomass of both macrofauna and meiofauna. No significant seasonal differences were documented by multiple regression models for the normalized biomass and size classes. The slope of a linear relationship between normalized biomass and size classes was − 0.54 ± 0.02 indicating a productive system, compared to ecosystems like estuaries. Summer–winter invariability of size spectra suggests that benthic community functioning in this Arctic fjordic system is relatively independent from the seasonality in the supply of organic matter produced in water column.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s00300-019-02515-2</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\PYTTP9F2\Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2019 - Seasonal constancy (summer vs. winter) of benthic .pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:34:51</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Gromisz, Sławomira</author><author>Legeżyńska, Joanna</author><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>First records of Lacydonia eliasoni Hartmann-Schröder, 1996 (Polychaeta: Phyllodocida) in the European Arctic</title><secondary-title>Polish Polar Research</secondary-title><short-title>First records of Lacydonia eliasoni Hartmann-Schröder, 1996 (Polychaeta</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Polish Polar Research</full-title></periodical><pages>175-185</pages><volume>38</volume><number>2</number><issue>2</issue><dates><year>2017</year><pub-dates><date>2017-06-27</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2081-8262</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1515/popore-2017-0011</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Lacydonia (Polychaeta: Phyllodocida) is a poorly known genus containing 16 species that are sporadically collected in low densities all over the world oceans. During three cruises (in June 2014 in Ullsfjorden, northern Norway, in January 2015 in Kongsfjorden, and in June 2012 in Smeerenburg, Svalbard) nine specimens of Lacydonia eliasoni were found on sandy and muddy sediments at depths from 180 to 350 m. All specimens were incomplete and consisted of 10 to 29 chaetigers. This study presents the first record of the Lacydonia genus in the waters of Svalbard as well as the first record of L. eliasoni in coastal waters off northern Norway. This species has been reported previously in the Skagerrak and Trondheimsfjorden (southern Norway), our findings therefore may indicate a northward extension of its range, possibly due to climate changes.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://journals.pan.pl/dlibra/publication/116062/edition/100873/content</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\VT5YA2YW\Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2017 - First records of Lacydonia eliasoni Hartmann-Schrö.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:34:37</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Kotwicki, L.</author><author>Weslawski, J.M.</author><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, M.</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, M.</author><author>Wenne, R.</author><author>Zbawicka, M.</author><author>Minchin, D.</author><author>Olenin, S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The re-appearance of the Mytilus spp. complex in Svalbard, Arctic, during the Holocene: The case for an arrival by anthropogenic flotsam</title><secondary-title>Global and Planetary Change</secondary-title><short-title>The re-appearance of the Mytilus spp. complex in Svalbard, Arctic, during the Holocene</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global and Planetary Change</full-title><abbr-1>Global and Planetary Change</abbr-1></periodical><pages>103502</pages><volume>202</volume><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>07/2021</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>09218181</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gloplacha.2021.103502</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The blue mussel Mytilus spp. complex has re-appeared in the high Arctic in Svalbard after a thousand years, with the first recent indication of its appearance in 2002 at the mouth of Isfjorden on the west coast. We examine its genetic affinity to selected North Atlantic populations and the modes of spread that may be responsible for its recent re-colonisation. We record here its distribution on Svalbard archipelago along the north-western coastline and within Isfjorden collected over a seven years period. We record for the first time the intertidal occurrence that includes a presence close to a glacier front. Genetic composition of mussels Mytilus spp. from different Svalbard locations reveal similarities mainly with populations of M. edulis, M. trossulus and their hybrid from Western Europe, Faroe Island, Scotland and Norway. The re-introduction to Svalbard most probably involved shipping and natural or anthropogenic flotsam. It seems that a new transport vector - large plastic debris - plays a significant role in this process.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0921818121000874</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\SIM654ZS\Kotwicki et al. - 2021 - The re-appearance of the Mytilus spp. complex in S.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:34:18</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Meyer-Kaiser, Kirstin</author><author>Sweetman, Andrew K.</author><author>Renaud, Paul E.</author><author>Włodarska–Kowalczuk, Maria</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Megabenthic standing stocks and organic carbon demand in a warming Arctic</title><secondary-title>Progress in Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Progress in Oceanography</full-title><abbr-1>Progress in Oceanography</abbr-1></periodical><pages>102616</pages><volume>196</volume><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>08/2021</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>00796611</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.pocean.2021.102616</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Benthic megafauna (organisms large enough to be visible on seabed photographs) are regarded as important for carbon cycling in benthic habitats. They are a food source for many predators like fish and marine mammals and may stimulate carbon mineralization in sediment by bioturbation. However, few studies address these basic characteristics of megabenthos quantitatively. This study quantifies the spatial variability in standing stock (biomass) and functioning (secondary production, respiration and carbon demand) of benthic megafauna in fjords and on the continental shelf of Svalbard. Organisms were measured from sea bottom images to assess their biomass using length-weight relationships and volumetric methods, then respiration and production were esti­ mated with empirical artificial neural network models. Significantly higher standing stock, secondary produc­ tion, respiration, and carbon demand were found in fjords categorized as ‘cold’ (as defined by water temperature, prevailing water masses and ice-cover) than in the ‘warm’ ones. Cold fjords were dominated by Echinodermata, while in warm fjords Crustacea prevailed. All megafaunal community parameters were negatively correlated with bottom temperature. It was not possible to assess specific direct impacts of temperature, and indirect effects may be more relevant to our findings. These include temperature-driven changes in primary production, ice cover and ice-algae production or predation pressure from carnivores expanding their ranges northward. The progression of climate warming may affect megafaunal communities by reducing their biomass, production, and carbon demand and have profound effects on ecosystem functioning.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0079661121001038</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\KE3R3JVG\Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2021 - Megabenthic standing stocks and organic carbon dem.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:34:05</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Martinez, Paula Sancho</author><author>Konwent, Weronika</author><author>Deja, Kajetan</author><author>Kotwicki, Lech</author><author>Węsławski, Jan Marcin</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Plastic contamination of sandy beaches along the southern Baltic – a one season field survey results</title><secondary-title>Oceanologia</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Oceanologia</full-title><abbr-1>Oceanologia</abbr-1></periodical><pages>769-780</pages><volume>64</volume><number>4</number><issue>4</issue><dates><year>2022</year><pub-dates><date>10/2022</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>00783234</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.oceano.2022.07.004</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The subject of this study was microplastics (&gt;32 μm), large micro-/macroplastics (&gt;2 mm) and plastic litter (visible by naked eye) contamination on sandy beaches and in coastal waters along the Polish coast of the Baltic Sea. Microplastics were studied with particular attention, with simultaneous observations in the water and across the beach. Other data was intended to serve as a background and as possible sources of microplastics. Most of the microplastics found were ﬁbers &lt;1 mm long, with blue ﬁbers dominating, followed by transparent, red and green ones, both in sand and water samples. The concentration of microplastics on the beach sand ranged from 118 to 1382 pieces kg−1, while in coastal waters from 0.61 to 2.76 pieces dm−3. As for large micro-/macroplastics and plastic litter, there was no dominant litter along the coast. The amount of large micro-/macroplastics ranged from 2 to 124 pieces m−2 (or from 0.13 to 44.30 g m−2). Regarding plastic litter, on average between 0.03 and 6.15 litter debris m−2 were found (or from 0.007 to 4.600 g m−2). The study conﬁrms that plastic pollution of the Polish coastal zone is a signiﬁcant problem comparable with both the rest of the Baltic Sea and other seas and oceans. Similar color-based composition of microplastics among all studied sites suggests that they may have a common source, while the contamination of large micro-/macroplastics and plastic litter (both amount of particles and their composition) along the Polish coast is highly site-speciﬁc and may be inﬂuenced by various local factors.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S007832342200080X</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\5EG7K6MX\Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2022 - Plastic contamination of sandy beaches along the s.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:33:17</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Jankowska, Emilia</author><author>Kotwicki, Lech</author><author>Damrat, Mateusz</author><author>Zajączkowski, Marek</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Effects of fluvial discharges on meiobenthic and macrobenthic variability in the Vistula River prodelta (Baltic Sea)</title><secondary-title>Journal of Marine Systems</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Marine Systems</full-title><abbr-1>Journal of Marine Systems</abbr-1></periodical><pages>135-146</pages><volume>157</volume><keywords><keyword>Meiofauna</keyword><keyword>Baltic Sea</keyword><keyword>Benthos</keyword><keyword>Community structure</keyword><keyword>Disturbance</keyword><keyword>Diversity</keyword><keyword>Macrofauna</keyword><keyword>Organic matter</keyword><keyword>River prodelta</keyword><keyword>Seasonality</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year><pub-dates><date>2016-05-01</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>0924-7963</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.jmarsys.2015.12.009</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The role of environmental variability produced by river discharges in shaping the spatial and seasonal patterns of meiobenthic and macrobenthic communities was studied in the Vistula River (Baltic Sea) prodelta. Seven stations located in the delta front, the plume influence area and the distal zone of the prodelta were visited over the four seasons of 2012. Meiofauna, macrofauna, water (temperature, salinity, and suspended matter) and sediments (grain size, POC, TN, δ15N and δ13C and photosynthetic pigments) were analysed. The seasonal variations in the river discharges (with maximum flows in spring) resulted in a strong temporal variability in the studied environmental characteristics. In the benthic biota, the signals of seasonal variability, if present, were much weaker than spatial zonation. The benthic communities inhabiting the delta front where the main bulk of fluvial materials was deposited were taxonomically impoverished. The richest fauna dwelled within the plume influence area where the physical disturbance ceased and primary marine production was enhanced by river transported nutrients. In the distal zone outside the river influence, the fauna was dominated by deeper dwelling species, and the numbers of individuals and taxa decreased. Factors related to the riverine discharges (i.e., salinity, mineral suspension, POC and δ13C in the water and sediments) were identified as having high correlation with variability in the meiofaunal and macrofaunal community descriptors. Evidently, the interplay of food (i.e., the quantity and quality of organic matter) and disturbance (i.e., the deposition of river transported minerals) constraints shaped the patterns of benthic variability in the prodelta of the second largest river entering the Baltic Sea.</abstract><remote-database-name>ScienceDirect</remote-database-name><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0924796315002341</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\E5NQLVYX\Włodarska-Kowalczuk et al. - 2016 - Effects of fluvial discharges on meiobenthic and m.pdf</url></pdf-urls><text-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\9GD7NBUX\S0924796315002341.html</url></text-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:31:20</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Górska, Barbara</author><author>Jankowska, Emilia</author><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Assessment of nematode biomass in marine sediments: A semi-automated image analysis method</title><secondary-title>Limnology and Oceanography: Methods</secondary-title><short-title>Assessment of nematode biomass in marine sediments</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Limnology and Oceanography: Methods</full-title></periodical><pages>816-827</pages><volume>14</volume><number>12</number><issue>12</issue><dates><year>2016</year><pub-dates><date>2016</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>1541-5856</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/lom3.10128</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Meiofaunal biomass, despite its ecological importance, is rarely assessed in marine ecological studies due to time-consuming and costly indirect procedures or inaccurate direct methods. Here, we present a semi-automated image analysis method for obtaining the widths and lengths of photographed nematodes that employs the Leica LAS Image Analysis module and is used to estimate Nematoda (a dominant marine meiofaunal taxon) biomass. Samples of 100 individual nematodes from 10 replicate samples representing two different environments (muddy fjord bottom and seagrass-vegetated sands) were used for the analyses, which were performed manually and semi-automatically. Manual measurements were taken by three independent analysts to check for individual differences. The automated measurements were collected almost two times faster than the manual ones. The three analysts and the computer did not differ in their assessments of nematode length, but significant differences existed among the measurements of maximum width by the three analysts (due to different designations of the point of nematode maximum width required by the manual method). For estimating individual nematode biomass, a formula using the equation for the volume of cylinder (one of the three tested in the study) is recommended. The total nematode biomass values obtained with this method were comparable to those reported from similar habitats. This semi-automated method seems to be less biased and more time and cost effective compared with standard manual protocols. The wider application of this method should facilitate the more frequent inclusion of meiofaunal biomass assessments in marine benthic surveys.</abstract><remote-database-name>Wiley Online Library</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/lom3.10128</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\AA4NPBU9\Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2016 - Assessment of nematode biomass in marine sediments.pdf</url></pdf-urls><text-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\W2X8F4V8\lom3.html</url></text-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:30:49</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Górska, Barbara</author><author>Michel, Loïc N.</author><author>Jankowska, Emilia</author><author>Zaborska, Agata</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Organic Carbon Origin, Benthic Faunal Consumption, and Burial in Sediments of Northern Atlantic and Arctic Fjords (60–81°N)</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences</full-title></periodical><pages>3737-3751</pages><volume>124</volume><number>12</number><issue>12</issue><keywords><keyword>benthic carbon mineralization</keyword><keyword>early diagenesis</keyword><keyword>marine geochemistry</keyword><keyword>organic carbon sequestration</keyword><keyword>s: organic matter preservation</keyword><keyword>sedimentary processes</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2019</year><pub-dates><date>2019</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2169-8961</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2019JG005140</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Fjords have been recently recognized as hot spots of organic carbon (Corg) sequestration in marine sediments. This study aims to identify regional and local drivers of variability of Corg burial in north Atlantic and Arctic fjords. We provide a comparative quantification of Corg, δ13C, photosynthetic pigments content, benthic biomass, consumption, Corg accumulation, and burial rates in sediments in six fjords (60–81°N). Higher sediment Corg content in southern Norway reflected longer phytoplankton growth season and higher productivity. Higher contributions of terrestrial Corg were noted in temperate/southern Norway (dense land vegetation and high precipitation) and Arctic/Svalbard (glacial erosion) than in subarctic/northern Norway locations. Benthic biomass and carbon consumption were best correlated to δ13C and photosynthetic pigments content indicating control by quality rather than quantity of available food. Benthic faunal consumption did not seem to affect the variability in Corg burial. Regional environmental factors (water temperature and latitude) combined with local factors (Corg, grain size, and pigment concentration) explained 94% of Corg burial variability. Based on the present study and literature data on Corg content, origin, and burial rates, the fjords were classified into four categories: temperate, subarctic, Arctic with glaciers, and Arctic without glaciers. The variability in marine productivity, terrestrial inflows, and carbon sequestration in fjords must be considered for global estimates of their role in blue carbon storage and for building scenarios of future changes in the course of climate warming.</abstract><remote-database-name>Wiley Online Library</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2019JG005140</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\5VE9IFG9\Włodarska-Kowalczuk et al. - 2019 - Organic Carbon Origin, Benthic Faunal Consumption,.pdf</url></pdf-urls><text-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\YBJGWSV7\2019JG005140.html</url></text-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:27:55</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Górska, Barbara</author><author>Renaud, Paul E.</author><author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Latitudinal consistency of biomass size spectra - benthic resilience despite environmental, taxonomic and functional trait variability</title><secondary-title>Scientific Reports</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Scientific Reports</full-title><abbr-1>Sci Rep</abbr-1></periodical><pages>4164</pages><volume>10</volume><number>1</number><issue>1</issue><keywords><keyword>Climate-change ecology</keyword><keyword>Community ecology</keyword><keyword>Marine biology</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year><pub-dates><date>2020-03-05</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2045-2322</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1038/s41598-020-60889-4</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Global warming is expected to cause reductions in organism body size, a fundamental biological unit important in determining biological processes. Possible effects of increasing temperature on biomass size spectra in coastal benthic communities were investigated. We hypothesized higher proportions of smaller size classes in warmer conditions. Soft bottom infauna samples were collected in six Norwegian and Svalbard fjords, spanning wide latitudinal (60–81°N) and bottom water temperature gradients (from −2 to 8 °C). Investigated fjords differed in terms of environmental settings (e.g., pigments or organic carbon in sediments). The slopes of normalised biomass size spectra (NBSS) did not differ among the fjords, while the benthic biomass and NBSS intercepts varied and were related to chlorophyll a and δ13C in sediments. The size spectra based on both abundance and biomass remained consistent, regardless of the strong variability in macrofauna taxonomic and functional trait composition. Variable relationships between temperature and body size were noted for particular taxa. Our results indicate that while benthic biomass depends on the nutritional quality of organic matter, its partitioning among size classes is consistent and independent of environmental and biological variability. The observed size structure remains a persistent feature of studied communities and may be resilient to major climatic changes.</abstract><remote-database-name>www.nature.com</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-60889-4</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\2UK9SUP5\Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2020 - Latitudinal consistency of biomass size spectra - .pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:27:30</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pouch, Anna</author><author>Zaborska, Agata</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Winogradow, Aleksandra</author><author>Pazdro, Ksenia</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>PCBs, HCB and PAHs in the seawater of Arctic fjords – Distribution, sources and risk assessment</title><secondary-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</full-title><abbr-1>Marine Pollution Bulletin</abbr-1></periodical><pages>111980</pages><volume>164</volume><keywords><keyword>Arctic</keyword><keyword>Hexachlorobenzene (HCB)</keyword><keyword>Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs)</keyword><keyword>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs)</keyword><keyword>Seawater</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>2021-03-01</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>0025-326X</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.marpolbul.2021.111980</electronic-resource-num><abstract>In the present study, we examine contamination with PCBs, HCB and PAHs in the seawater of Arctic fjords (Hornsund, Kongsfjorden and Adventfjorden) which differ in environmental conditions and are particularly sensitive to climate change. We also investigate how the melting glaciers and ocean currents may affect the distribution and fate of target compounds in the seawater column in the fjords. The ∑7 PCB, HCB and ∑12 PAH concentrations in seawater ranged from, respectively: 0.002 to 41.2 ng/L; from LOQ to 233 ng/L; and from 0.196 to 311 ng/L. The research indicates that the concentrations of contaminants detected in Arctic fjords depend on the physicochemical properties of these compounds, local human activity and occurrence of glacier meltwaters. Detected HCB and PAH concentrations in most of the seawater samples were at levels classified as harmless, however in 30 out of 80 analysed suspended particulate matter samples some compounds were present at toxic levels.</abstract><remote-database-name>ScienceDirect</remote-database-name><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X2100014X</url></web-urls><text-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\KNG59PPG\S0025326X2100014X.html</url></text-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:26:33</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Węsławski, Jan Marcin</author><author>Legeżyńska, Joanna</author><author>Kotwicki, Lech</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Olenin, Sergej</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Gammarus (Amphipoda) species competitive exclusion or coexistence as a result of climate change in the Arctic?</title><secondary-title>Polish Polar Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Polish Polar Research</full-title></periodical><pages>287-302</pages><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>2021</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2081-8262</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.24425/ppr.2021.138586</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Polska Akademia Nauk</abstract><remote-database-name>journals.pan.pl</remote-database-name><urls><web-urls><url>https://journals.pan.pl/dlibra/show-content?id=120613</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\X5HILS3K\Węsławski et al. - 2021 - Gammarus (Amphipoda) species competitive exclusion.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2024-01-03 20:21:42</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Jaroměřská, Tereza Novotná</author><author>Ambrosini, Roberto</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Franzetti, Andrea</author><author>Klimaszyk, Piotr</author><author>Rozwalak, Piotr</author><author>Poniecka, Ewa</author><author>Vondrovicová, Lenka</author><author>Zawierucha, Krzysztof</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Spatial distribution and stable isotopic composition of invertebrates uncover differences between habitats on the glacier surface in the Alps</title><secondary-title>Limnology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Limnology</full-title><abbr-1>Limnology</abbr-1></periodical><pages>83-93</pages><volume>24</volume><number>2</number><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Collembola</keyword><keyword>Cryoconite holes</keyword><keyword>Stable isotopes</keyword><keyword>Supraglacial debris</keyword><keyword>Tardigrada</keyword><keyword>Weathering crust</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023-04-01</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>1439-863X</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s10201-023-00713-w</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Glacier surfaces are the most biologically productive parts of glaciers with a variety of organisms and habitats. However, distinctiveness of habitats and communities of dominant invertebrate consumers on the ice surface is poorly documented. We focused on dominant consumers in three supraglacial (on the glacier surface) habitats on the alpine glacier Forni – cryoconite holes (water-filled reservoirs with a thin layer of sediment at the bottom), supraglacial debris (layer of stones and gravel covering glacier surface), and surface ice of the weathering crust. We analyzed carbon and nitrogen contents and stable isotope ratios (δ13C, δ15N), organic matter (OM) content, biomass of consumers, and the community composition of consumers to investigate differences between supraglacial habitats. In cryoconite holes, tardigrades (Tardigrada) were dominant consumers. In supraglacial debris, only springtails (Collembola) occurred mainly between stones and ice. No active animals were found in the surface ice of the weathering crust. Carbon and nitrogen contents, δ13C, and δ15N of invertebrates and OM differed between habitats. Cryoconite was enriched in OM with high δ13C and low δ15N compared to supraglacial debris likely indicating differences in major components of OM serving as food of invertebrates. Also, the OM, and carbon and nitrogen contents differed between habitats with the highest concentration in cryoconite. The dry biomass of tardigrades was similar compared to springtails. We present the first observation of differences between supraglacial habitats in the Alps based on the community composition of invertebrates, OM and stable isotopes. This initial study highlights the importance of differences in habitats and its consumers in the functioning of supraglacial ecosystem.</abstract><remote-database-name>Springer Link</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10201-023-00713-w</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\Q5DUPJAV\Jaroměřská et al. - 2023 - Spatial distribution and stable isotopic compositi.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2023-12-01 16:15:15</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Piwoni-Piórewicz, Anna</author><author>Liow, Lee Hsiang</author><author>Krzemińska, Małgorzata</author><author>Chełchowski, Maciej</author><author>Iglikowska, Anna</author><author>Ronco, Fabrizia</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Smith, Abigail M.</author><author>Gordon, Dennis P.</author><author>Waeschenbach, Andrea</author><author>Najorka, Jens</author><author>Figuerola, Blanca</author><author>Boonzaaier-Davids, Melissa K.</author><author>Achilleos, Katerina</author><author>Mello, Hannah</author><author>Florence, Wayne K.</author><author>Vieira, Leandro M.</author><author>Ostrovsky, Andrew N.</author><author>Shunatova, Natalia</author><author>Porter, Joanne S.</author><author>Sokolover, Noga</author><author>Cumming, Robyn L.</author><author>Novosel, Maja</author><author>O'Dea, Aaron</author><author>Lombardi, Chiara</author><author>Jain, Sudhanshi S.</author><author>Huang, Danwei</author><author>Kukliński, Piotr</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Skeletal mineralogy of marine calcifying organisms shaped by seawater temperature and evolutionary history—A case study of cheilostome bryozoans</title><secondary-title>Global Ecology and Biogeography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global Ecology and Biogeography</full-title></periodical><pages>e13874</pages><volume>33</volume><number>8</number><issue>8</issue><keywords><keyword>aragonite</keyword><keyword>biomineralization</keyword><keyword>calcifiers</keyword><keyword>calcite</keyword><keyword>marine invertebrates</keyword><keyword>phylogeny</keyword><keyword>skeleton</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>1466-8238</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/geb.13874</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Aim Quantify the contribution of environmental factors (water temperature, salinity and depth) and evolutionary history to varied skeletal mineralogy in calcifying marine organisms. Location Global Ocean. Time period Present. Major taxa studied Order: Cheilostomatida; Phylum: Bryozoa. Methods We employed X-ray diffraction (XRD) to analyse the skeletal mineral composition of 872 individual colonies, representing 437 bryozoan species, in terms of calcite/aragonite ratios. We integrated these data with equivalent published data, thus reaching 981 species, and applied linear models (LMs), generalized linear models (GLMs) and phylogenetic generalized least squares models (PGLSs) to investigate the influences of temperature, salinity, depth and phylogenetic history on the mineralogy of nearly 1000 cheilostome bryozoan species. Results Cheilostome bryozoans vary considerably in their skeletal mineral composition: in our dataset 65% of the species possess purely calcite skeletons, 15% exclusively employ aragonite and 20% exhibit mixed (i.e. calcite and aragonite) mineralogies. Temperature is the predominant measured environmental factor influencing bryozoan skeletal mineralogy, accounting for 20% of its variability across species, when phylogenetic relatedness is unaccounted for. Bryozoans in lower latitudes, characterized by higher seawater temperatures, have higher aragonite concentrations. By accounting for phylogenetic structure using a subset of 87 species for which we have topological information, 40% of the observed mineralogical variability could be attributed to present-day temperature. In contrast, depth and salinity played minor roles, explaining less than 1% of the mineralogical variation each. Main conclusions This study emphasizes the influence of evolutionary history on the mineralogical variability of calcifying organisms, even when it can be shown that a single environmental factor (temperature) explains a substantial amount of this variability. When confronted with changing temperature, calcifiers such as bryozoans are likely to respond in diverse ways, depending on the species, given their phylogenetic relatedness and the external conditions they meet.</abstract><remote-database-name>Wiley Online Library</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/geb.13874</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\mikol\OneDrive\Pulpit\literature\Global Ecology and Biogeography - 2024 - Piwoni‐Piórewicz - Skeletal mineralogy of marine calcifying organisms shaped by.pdf</url></pdf-urls><text-urls><url>C:\Users\mikolaj.mazurkiewi\Zotero\storage\Z3PT5TGP\geb.html</url></text-urls></urls><access-date>2024-06-13 12:13:24</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lubośny, Marek</author><author>Annasawmy, Pavanee</author><author>Burgués Martínez, Itziar</author><author>Turk Dermastia, Timotej</author><author>Espasandín, Lucía</author><author>Fernandes, Joana Filipa</author><author>Fontela, Marcos</author><author>Galobart, Cristina</author><author>Garcia-Garin, Odei</author><author>Gregório, Inês</author><author>Llopis Monferrer, Natalia</author><author>López-Acosta, María</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Piñeiro-Juncal, Nerea</author><author>Schadeberg, Amanda</author><author>Scopetani, Costanza</author><author>Sowa, Anna</author><author>Suaria, Giuseppe</author><author>Tsiola, Anastasia</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>How institutions can better support international early-career researchers</title><secondary-title>Nature Human Behaviour</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Nature Human Behaviour</full-title><abbr-1>Nat Hum Behav</abbr-1></periodical><pages>421-423</pages><volume>9</volume><dates><year>2025</year><pub-dates><date>2025-02-24</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2397-3374</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1038/s41562-025-02125-5</electronic-resource-num><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-025-02125-5</url></web-urls></urls><access-date>2025-02-25 09:17:30</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fabrizi, Francesca</author><author>Spagnuolo, Damiano</author><author>Bottari, Teresa</author><author>Mghili, Bilal</author><author>Branca, Caterina</author><author>Punzo, Elisa</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Nibali, Valeria Conti</author><author>Genovese, Giuseppa</author><author>D’Angelo, Giovanna</author><author>Mancuso, Monique</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Plastic pollution in brackish waters: Macroalgae as collectors of plastic debris</title><secondary-title>Journal of Hazardous Materials</secondary-title><short-title>Plastic pollution in brackish waters</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Hazardous Materials</full-title><abbr-1>Journal of Hazardous Materials</abbr-1></periodical><pages>139114</pages><volume>495</volume><dates><year>2025</year><pub-dates><date>09/2025</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>03043894</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.jhazmat.2025.139114</electronic-resource-num><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0304389425020308</url></web-urls></urls><access-date>2025-10-28 09:02:28</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dąbrowska, Anna Maria</author><author>McGovern, Maeve</author><author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author><author>Poste, Amanda</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Seasonal patterns and environmental drivers of protistan plankton along a terrestrial–marine gradient in Isfjorden (Svalbard)</title><secondary-title>Frontiers in Marine Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Frontiers in Marine Science</full-title><abbr-1>Front. Mar. Sci.</abbr-1></periodical><pages>1631963</pages><volume>12</volume><dates><year>2025</year><pub-dates><date>2025-9-18</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2296-7745</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.3389/fmars.2025.1631963</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The Arctic is undergoing rapid environmental transformation, with intensified glacial and permafrost melt fundamentally altering freshwater discharge regimes and biogeochemical fluxes to coastal fjord systems. Here, we investigate how seasonal meltwater dynamics shape protistan plankton communities along a terrestrial – marine gradient in Isfjorden (Svalbard) during the exceptionally warm year of 2018. Sampling across three distinct melt season stages – pre-freshet (May), spring freshet (June), and late summer runoff (August) – revealed pronounced temporal and spatial shifts in community structure, strongly linked to evolving environmental gradients. In May, cold, clear, unstratified waters and marine nutrient inputs supported a typical late spring bloom, led by&#xD;              Phaeocystis pouchetii&#xD;              , which significantly contributed to the particulate organic carbon pool, and was followed by diatoms of the genera&#xD;              Chaetoceros&#xD;              and&#xD;              Thalassiosira&#xD;              . The June freshet triggered sharp stratification and nutrient enrichment from glacial and terrestrial sources, driving an unprecedented proliferation of small flagellates, notably&#xD;              Chrysochromulina&#xD;              and two morphologically distinct, yet unidentified taxa. However, by August, escalating turbidity from intensified meltwater inputs and sediment resuspension severely constrained photic conditions, suppressing protistan biomass despite sustained nutrient availability. Across the season, community dynamics were governed by complex interactions between nutrient supply, light limitation, and physical forcings such as stratification and advection. Our findings suggest that ongoing Arctic warming may increasingly favor opportunistic, small flagellates over traditional diatom-dominated blooms, with major implications for carbon cycling and food web dynamics in Arctic fjords.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmars.2025.1631963/full</url></web-urls></urls><access-date>2025-10-28 09:02:52</access-date></record></records></xml>