<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
  <records>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Kadac-Czapska, Kornelia</author>
          <author>Jutrzenka Trzebiatowska, Patrycja</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Kowalczyk, Piotr</author>
          <author>Knez, Eliza</author>
          <author>Behrendt, Mirosław</author>
          <author>Mahlik, Sebastian</author>
          <author>Zaleska-Medynska, Adriana</author>
          <author>Grembecka, Małgorzata</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Isolation and identification of microplastics in infant formulas – A potential health risk for children</title>
        <secondary-title>Food Chemistry</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Food Chemistry</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>138246</pages>
      <volume>440</volume>
      <issue>December 2023</issue>
      <keywords/>
      <dates>
        <year>2024</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.138246</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Kadac-Czapska et al. - 2024 - Isolation and identification of microplastics in infant formulas – A potential health risk for children -.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0308814623028649</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <cid>15227162335336107066</cid>
      <google_cites>1</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Jaroměřská, Tereza Novotná</author>
          <author>Ambrosini, Roberto</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Franzetti, Andrea</author>
          <author>Klimaszyk, Piotr</author>
          <author>Rozwalak, Piotr</author>
          <author>Poniecka, Ewa</author>
          <author>Vondrovicová, Lenka</author>
          <author>Zawierucha, Krzysztof</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Spatial distribution and stable isotopic composition of invertebrates uncover differences between habitats on the glacier surface in the Alps</title>
        <secondary-title>Limnology</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Limnology</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>83-93</pages>
      <volume>24</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Collembola</keyword>
        <keyword>Cryoconite holes</keyword>
        <keyword>Stable isotopes</keyword>
        <keyword>Supraglacial debris</keyword>
        <keyword>Tardigrada</keyword>
        <keyword>Weathering crust</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2023</year>
      </dates>
      <publisher>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher>
      <isbn>0123456789</isbn>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s10201-023-00713-w</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Jaroměřská et al. - 2023 - Spatial distribution and stable isotopic composition of invertebrates uncover differences between habitats on.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10201-023-00713-w</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Glacier surfaces are the most biologically productive parts of glaciers with a variety of organisms and habitats. However, distinctiveness of habitats and communities of dominant invertebrate consumers on the ice surface is poorly documented. We focused on dominant consumers in three supraglacial (on the glacier surface) habitats on the alpine glacier Forni – cryoconite holes (water-filled reservoirs with a thin layer of sediment at the bottom), supraglacial debris (layer of stones and gravel covering glacier surface), and surface ice of the weathering crust. We analyzed carbon and nitrogen contents and stable isotope ratios (δ13C, δ15N), organic matter (OM) content, biomass of consumers, and the community composition of consumers to investigate differences between supraglacial habitats. In cryoconite holes, tardigrades (Tardigrada) were dominant consumers. In supraglacial debris, only springtails (Collembola) occurred mainly between stones and ice. No active animals were found in the surface ice of the weathering crust. Carbon and nitrogen contents, δ13C, and δ15N of invertebrates and OM differed between habitats. Cryoconite was enriched in OM with high δ13C and low δ15N compared to supraglacial debris likely indicating differences in major components of OM serving as food of invertebrates. Also, the OM, and carbon and nitrogen contents differed between habitats with the highest concentration in cryoconite. The dry biomass of tardigrades was similar compared to springtails. We present the first observation of differences between supraglacial habitats in the Alps based on the community composition of invertebrates, OM and stable isotopes. This initial study highlights the importance of differences in habitats and its consumers in the functioning of supraglacial ecosystem.</abstract>
      <cid>12732748239548719735</cid>
      <google_cites>2</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Ferrero, Luca</author>
          <author>Scibetta, Lorenzo</author>
          <author>Markuszewski, Piotr</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikolaj</author>
          <author>Drozdowska, Violetta</author>
          <author>Makuch, Przemysław</author>
          <author>Jutrzenka-Trzebiatowska, Patrycja</author>
          <author>Zaleska-Medynska, Adriana</author>
          <author>Andò, Sergio</author>
          <author>Saliu, Francesco</author>
          <author>Nilsson, Douglas E.</author>
          <author>Bolzacchini, E.</author>
          <author>Nilsson, E. Douglas</author>
          <author>Bolzacchini, E.</author>
          <author>Nilsson, Douglas E.</author>
          <author>Bolzacchini, E.</author>
          <author>Nilsson, E. Douglas</author>
          <author>Bolzacchini, E.</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Airborne and marine microplastics from an oceanographic survey at the Baltic Sea: An emerging role of air-sea interaction?</title>
        <secondary-title>Science of The Total Environment</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Science of The Total Environment</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>153709</pages>
      <volume>824</volume>
      <keywords/>
      <dates>
        <year>2022</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.153709</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Ferrero et al. - 2022 - Airborne and marine microplastics from an oceanographic survey at the Baltic Sea An emerging role of air-sea int.pdf</url>
          <url>internal-pdf://Ferrero et al. - 2022 - Airborne and marine microplastics from an oceanographic survey at the Baltic Sea An emerging role of air-sea (2).pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0048969722008014</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <cid>15373259585579930287</cid>
      <google_cites>53</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Martinez, Paula Sancho</author>
          <author>Konwent, Weronika</author>
          <author>Deja, Kajetan</author>
          <author>Kotwicki, Lech</author>
          <author>Węsławski, Jan Marcin</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Plastic contamination of sandy beaches along the southern Baltic – a one season field survey results</title>
        <secondary-title>Oceanologia</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Oceanologia</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>769-780</pages>
      <volume>64</volume>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Baltic Sea</keyword>
        <keyword>Coastal zone</keyword>
        <keyword>Marine litter</keyword>
        <keyword>Microplastic</keyword>
        <keyword>Sources</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2022</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.oceano.2022.07.004</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2022 - Plastic contamination of sandy beaches along the southern Baltic – a one season field survey results - O(2).pdf</url>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2022 - Plastic contamination of sandy beaches along the southern Baltic – a one season field survey results - Ocea.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S007832342200080X</url>
          <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oceano.2022.07.004</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>The subject of this study was microplastics (&gt;32 µm), large micro-/macroplastics (&gt;2 mm) and plastic litter (visible by naked eye) contamination on sandy beaches and in coastal waters along the Polish coast of the Baltic Sea. Microplastics were studied with particular attention, with simultaneous observations in the water and across the beach. Other data was intended to serve as a background and as possible sources of microplastics. Most of the microplastics found were fibers &lt;1 mm long, with blue fibers dominating, followed by transparent, red and green ones, both in sand and water samples. The concentration of microplastics on the beach sand ranged from 118 to 1382 pieces kg−1, while in coastal waters from 0.61 to 2.76 pieces dm−3. As for large micro-/macroplastics and plastic litter, there was no dominant litter along the coast. The amount of large micro-/macroplastics ranged from 2 to 124 pieces m−2 (or from 0.13 to 44.30 g m−2). Regarding plastic litter, on average between 0.03 and 6.15 litter debris m−2 were found (or from 0.007 to 4.600 g m−2). The study confirms that plastic pollution of the Polish coastal zone is a significant problem comparable with both the rest of the Baltic Sea and other seas and oceans. Similar color-based composition of microplastics among all studied sites suggests that they may have a common source, while the contamination of large micro-/macroplastics and plastic litter (both amount of particles and their composition) along the Polish coast is highly site-specific and may be influenced by various local factors.</abstract>
      <cid>16333498054316694152</cid>
      <google_cites>3</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Kotwicki, L.</author>
          <author>Weslawski, J. M.</author>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, M.</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, M.</author>
          <author>Wenne, R.</author>
          <author>Zbawicka, M.</author>
          <author>Minchin, D.</author>
          <author>Olenin, S.</author>
          <author>W, M</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, M.</author>
          <author>Wenne, R.</author>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, M.</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, M.</author>
          <author>Wenne, R.</author>
          <author>Zbawicka, M.</author>
          <author>Minchin, D.</author>
          <author>Olenin, S.</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>The re-appearance of the Mytilus spp. complex in Svalbard, Arctic, during the Holocene: The case for an arrival by anthropogenic flotsam</title>
        <secondary-title>Global and Planetary Change</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Global and Planetary Change</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>103502</pages>
      <volume>202</volume>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Arctic</keyword>
        <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
        <keyword>Global change</keyword>
        <keyword>Mytilus spp.</keyword>
        <keyword>Plastic litter</keyword>
        <keyword>Re-introduction</keyword>
        <keyword>Vectors</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gloplacha.2021.103502</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Kotwicki et al. - 2021 - The re-appearance of the Mytilus spp. complex in Svalbard, Arctic, during the Holocene The case for an arrival.pdf</url>
          <url>internal-pdf://Kotwicki et al. - 2021 - The re-appearance of the Mytilus spp. complex in Svalbard, Arctic, during the Holocene The case for an arriv(2).pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0921818121000874</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>The blue mussel Mytilus spp. complex has re-appeared in the high Arctic in Svalbard after a thousand years, with the first recent indication of its appearance in 2002 at the mouth of Isfjorden on the west coast. We examine its genetic affinity to selected North Atlantic populations and the modes of spread that may be responsible for its recent re-colonisation. We record here its distribution on Svalbard archipelago along the north-western coastline and within Isfjorden collected over a seven years period. We record for the first time the intertidal occurrence that includes a presence close to a glacier front. Genetic composition of mussels Mytilus spp. from different Svalbard locations reveal similarities mainly with populations of M. edulis, M. trossulus and their hybrid from Western Europe, Faroe Island, Scotland and Norway. The re-introduction to Svalbard most probably involved shipping and natural or anthropogenic flotsam. It seems that a new transport vector - large plastic debris - plays a significant role in this process.</abstract>
      <cid>5573704949946846425</cid>
      <google_cites>18</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Węsławski, Jan Marcin</author>
          <author>Legeżyńska, Joanna</author>
          <author>Kotwicki, Lech</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Olenin, Sergej</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Gammarus (Amphipoda) species competitive exclusion or coexistence as a resultof climate change in the Arctic?</title>
        <secondary-title>Polish Polar Research</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Polish Polar Research</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>287-302</pages>
      <volume>42</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Arctic</keyword>
        <keyword>Peracarida</keyword>
        <keyword>Svalbard</keyword>
        <keyword>arctic</keyword>
        <keyword>climate change</keyword>
        <keyword>congeneric species</keyword>
        <keyword>peracarida</keyword>
        <keyword>svalbard</keyword>
        <keyword>sympatry</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.24425/ppr.2021.138586</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Węsławski et al. - 2021 - Gammarus (Amphipoda) species competitive exclusion or coexistence as a resultof climate change in the Arctic -.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://journals.pan.pl/dlibra/show-content?id=120613</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <cid>15197318823349045288</cid>
      <google_cites>3</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Meyer-Kaiser, Kirstin</author>
          <author>Sweetman, Andrew K</author>
          <author>Renaud, Paul E</author>
          <author>Włodarska–Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Megabenthic standing stocks and organic carbon demand in a warming Arctic</title>
        <secondary-title>Progress in Oceanography</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Progress in Oceanography</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>102616</pages>
      <volume>196</volume>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Benthos</keyword>
        <keyword>Respiration</keyword>
        <keyword>Seabed photography</keyword>
        <keyword>Secondary production</keyword>
        <keyword>Svalbard</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.pocean.2021.102616</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2021 - Megabenthic standing stocks and organic carbon demand in a warming Arctic - Progress in Oceanography.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pocean.2021.102616</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Benthic megafauna (organisms large enough to be visible on seabed photographs) are regarded as important for carbon cycling in benthic habitats. They are a food source for many predators like fish and marine mammals and may stimulate carbon mineralization in sediment by bioturbation. However, few studies address these basic characteristics of megabenthos quantitatively. This study quantifies the spatial variability in standing stock (biomass) and functioning (secondary production, respiration and carbon demand) of benthic megafauna in fjords and on the continental shelf of Svalbard. Organisms were measured from sea bottom images to assess their biomass using length-weight relationships and volumetric methods, then respiration and production were estimated with empirical artificial neural network models. Significantly higher standing stock, secondary production, respiration, and carbon demand were found in fjords categorized as ‘cold’ (as defined by water temperature, prevailing water masses and ice-cover) than in the ‘warm’ ones. Cold fjords were dominated by Echinodermata, while in warm fjords Crustacea prevailed. All megafaunal community parameters were negatively correlated with bottom temperature. It was not possible to assess specific direct impacts of temperature, and indirect effects may be more relevant to our findings. These include temperature-driven changes in primary production, ice cover and ice-algae production or predation pressure from carnivores expanding their ranges northward. The progression of climate warming may affect megafaunal communities by reducing their biomass, production, and carbon demand and have profound effects on ecosystem functioning.</abstract>
      <cid>3236217325495242357</cid>
      <google_cites>1</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Pouch, Anna</author>
          <author>Zaborska, Agata</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Winogradow, Aleksandra</author>
          <author>Pazdro, Ksenia</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>PCBs , HCB and PAHs in the seawater of Arctic fjords – Distribution, sources and risk assessment</title>
        <secondary-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <volume>164</volume>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>hcb</keyword>
        <keyword>hexachlorobenzene</keyword>
        <keyword>pahs</keyword>
        <keyword>pcbs</keyword>
        <keyword>polychlorinated biphenyls</keyword>
        <keyword>polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2021</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.marpolbul.2021.111980</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Pouch et al. - 2021 - PCBs , HCB and PAHs in the seawater of Arctic fjords – Distribution, sources and risk assessment - Marine Pollutio.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X2100014X</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <cid>16157326501337233762</cid>
      <google_cites>31</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Górska, Barbara</author>
          <author>Renaud, Paul E.</author>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Latitudinal consistency of biomass size spectra - benthic resilience despite environmental, taxonomic and functional trait variability</title>
        <secondary-title>Scientific Reports</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Scientific Reports</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>4164</pages>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>benthic biomass size spectra</keyword>
        <keyword>community structure</keyword>
        <keyword>resilience</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2020</year>
      </dates>
      <isbn>4159802060</isbn>
      <accession-num>32139715</accession-num>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1038/s41598-020-60889-4</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2020 - Latitudinal consistency of biomass size spectra - benthic resilience despite environmental, taxonomic and f.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>http://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-60889-4</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Global warming is expected to cause reductions in organism body size, a fundamental biological unit important in determining biological processes. Possible effects of increasing temperature on biomass size spectra in coastal benthic communities were investigated. We hypothesized higher proportions of smaller size classes in warmer conditions. Soft bottom infauna samples were collected in six Norwegian and Svalbard fjords, spanning wide latitudinal (60–81°N) and bottom water temperature gradients (from −2 to 8 °C). Investigated fjords differed in terms of environmental settings (e.g., pigments or organic carbon in sediments). The slopes of normalised biomass size spectra (NBSS) did not differ among the fjords, while the benthic biomass and NBSS intercepts varied and were related to chlorophyll a and δ13C in sediments. The size spectra based on both abundance and biomass remained consistent, regardless of the strong variability in macrofauna taxonomic and functional trait composition. Variable relationships between temperature and body size were noted for particular taxa. Our results indicate that while benthic biomass depends on the nutritional quality of organic matter, its partitioning among size classes is consistent and independent of environmental and biological variability. The observed size structure remains a persistent feature of studied communities and may be resilient to major climatic changes.</abstract>
      <cid>13464209655969765675</cid>
      <google_cites>18</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Górska, Barbara</author>
          <author>Michel, Loïc N.</author>
          <author>Jankowska, Emilia</author>
          <author>Zaborska, Agata</author>
          <author>Górska, Barbara</author>
          <author>Loïc, Michel, N.</author>
          <author>Jankowska, Emilia</author>
          <author>Zaborska, Agata</author>
          <author>Górska, Barbara</author>
          <author>Michel, Loïc N.</author>
          <author>Jankowska, Emilia</author>
          <author>Zaborska, Agata</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Organic Carbon Origin, Benthic Faunal Consumption, and Burial in Sediments of Northern Atlantic and Arctic Fjords (60–81°N)</title>
        <secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>3737-3751</pages>
      <volume>124</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>benthic carbon mineralization</keyword>
        <keyword>early diagenesis</keyword>
        <keyword>marine geochemistry</keyword>
        <keyword>organic carbon sequestration</keyword>
        <keyword>s: organic matter preservation</keyword>
        <keyword>sedimentary processes</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2019</year>
      </dates>
      <isbn>0000000159</isbn>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2019JG005140</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Włodarska-Kowalczuk et al. - 2019 - Organic Carbon Origin, Benthic Faunal Consumption, and Burial in Sediments of Northern (2).pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2019JG005140</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Fjords have been recently recognized as hot spots of organic carbon (Corg) sequestration in marine sediments. This study aims to identify regional and local drivers of variability of Corg burial in north Atlantic and Arctic fjords. We provide a comparative quantification of Corg, δ13C, photosynthetic pigments content, benthic biomass, consumption, Corg accumulation, and burial rates in sediments in six fjords (60–81°N). Higher sediment Corg content in southern Norway reflected longer phytoplankton growth season and higher productivity. Higher contributions of terrestrial Corg were noted in temperate/southern Norway (dense land vegetation and high precipitation) and Arctic/Svalbard (glacial erosion) than in subarctic/northern Norway locations. Benthic biomass and carbon consumption were best correlated to δ13C and photosynthetic pigments content indicating control by quality rather than quantity of available food. Benthic faunal consumption did not seem to affect the variability in Corg burial. Regional environmental factors (water temperature and latitude) combined with local factors (Corg, grain size, and pigment concentration) explained 94% of Corg burial variability. Based on the present study and literature data on Corg content, origin, and burial rates, the fjords were classified into four categories: temperate, subarctic, Arctic with glaciers, and Arctic without glaciers. The variability in marine productivity, terrestrial inflows, and carbon sequestration in fjords must be considered for global estimates of their role in blue carbon storage and for building scenarios of future changes in the course of climate warming.</abstract>
      <cid>9916549223428078689</cid>
      <google_cites>41</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Górska, Barbara</author>
          <author>Renaud, Paul E.</author>
          <author>Legeżyńska, Joanna</author>
          <author>Berge, Jørgen</author>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Seasonal constancy (summer vs. winter) of benthic size spectra in an Arctic fjord</title>
        <secondary-title>Polar Biology</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Polar Biology</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>1255-1270</pages>
      <volume>42</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Arctic winter</keyword>
        <keyword>Biomass</keyword>
        <keyword>Meiofauna</keyword>
        <keyword>Size spectra</keyword>
        <keyword>Zoobenthos</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2019</year>
      </dates>
      <publisher>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher>
      <isbn>0030001902515</isbn>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s00300-019-02515-2</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2019 - Seasonal constancy (summer vs. winter) of benthic size spectra in an Arctic fjord - Polar Biology.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s00300-019-02515-2</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Size spectra are important descriptors of community structure and can indicate changes in community functioning in response to shifts in environmental conditions. There are relatively few assessments of benthic size spectra, and most are based on summer samples alone. Processes influencing size spectra, such as recruitment and predation pressure, vary seasonally, and understanding this variation is necessary to interpret patterns in time or space. Here we compare summer and winter biomass size spectra in the central basin of Kongsfjorden (west Spitsbergen). We recorded seasonal changes in the quality of organic matter available to the benthos, indicated by higher chloroplastic pigments concentrations in surface sediments in summer, as well as in differences in total abundance and biomass of both macrofauna and meiofauna. No significant seasonal differences were documented by multiple regression models for the normalized biomass and size classes. The slope of a linear relationship between normalized biomass and size classes was − 0.54 ± 0.02 indicating a productive system, compared to ecosystems like estuaries. Summer–winter invariability of size spectra suggests that benthic community functioning in this Arctic fjordic system is relatively independent from the seasonality in the supply of organic matter produced in water column.</abstract>
      <cid>16193816948220095227</cid>
      <google_cites>16</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Gromisz, Sławomira</author>
          <author>Legezyńska, Joanna</author>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>First records of Lacydonia eliasoni Hartmann-Schröder, 1996 (Polychaeta: Phyllodocida) in the European Arctic</title>
        <secondary-title>Polish Polar Research</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Polish Polar Research</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>175-185</pages>
      <volume>38</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Arctic</keyword>
        <keyword>Lacydonia</keyword>
        <keyword>Polychaeta</keyword>
        <keyword>Spitsbergen</keyword>
        <keyword>range extension</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2017</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1515/popore-2017-0011</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2017 - First records of Lacydonia eliasoni Hartmann-Schröder, 1996 (Polychaeta Phyllodocida) in the European Arcti.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://doi.org/10.1515/popore-2017-0011</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Lacydonia (Polychaeta: Phyllodocida) is a poorly known genus containing 16 species that are sporadically collected in low densities all over the world oceans. During three cruises (in June 2014 in Ullsfjorden, northern Norway, in January 2015 in Kongsfjorden, and in June 2012 in Smeerenburg, Svalbard) nine specimens of Lacydonia eliasoni were found on sandy and muddy sediments at depths from 180 to 350 m. All specimens were incomplete and consisted of 10 to 29 chaetigers. This study presents the first record of the Lacydonia genus in the waters of Svalbard as well as the first record of L. eliasoni in coastal waters off northern Norway. This species has been reported previously in the Skagerrak and Trondheimsfjorden (southern Norway), our findings therefore may indicate a northward extension of its range, possibly due to climate changes.</abstract>
      <cid>9835473783041616334</cid>
      <google_cites>5</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Górska, Barbara</author>
          <author>Jankowska, Emilia</author>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Assessment of nematode biomass in marine sediments: A semi-automated image analysis method</title>
        <secondary-title>Limnology and Oceanography: Methods</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Limnology and Oceanography: Methods</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>816-827</pages>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <keywords/>
      <dates>
        <year>2016</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1002/lom3.10128</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Mazurkiewicz et al. - 2016 - Assessment of nematode biomass in marine sediments A semi-automated image analysis method - Limnology and O.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/lom3.10128</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>Meiofaunal biomass, despite its ecological importance, is rarely assessed in marine ecological studies due to time-consuming and costly indirect procedures or inaccurate direct methods. Here, we present a semiautomated image analysis method for obtaining the widths and lengths of photographed nematodes that employs the Leica LAS Image Analysis module and is used to estimate Nematoda (a dominant marine meiofaunal taxon) biomass. Samples of 100 individual nematodes from 10 replicate samples representing two different environments (muddy fjord bottom and seagrass-vegetated sands) were used for the analyses, which were performed manually and semi-automatically. Manual measurements were taken by three independent analysts to check for individual differences. The automated measurements were collected almost two times faster than the manual ones. The three analysts and the computer did not differ in their assessments of nematode length, but significant differences existed among the measurements of maximum width by the three analysts (due to different designations of the point of nematode maximum width required by the manual method). For estimating individual nematode biomass, a formula using the equation for the volume of cylinder (one of the three tested in the study) is recommended. The total nematode biomass values obtained with this method were comparable to those reported from similar habitats. This semi-automated method seems to be less biased and more time and cost effective compared with standard manual protocols. The wider application of this method should facilitate the more frequent inclusion of meiofaunal biomass assessments in marine benthic surveys.</abstract>
      <cid>18181534491168061680</cid>
      <google_cites>20</google_cites>
    </record>
    <record>
      <database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database>
      <ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type>
      <contributors>
        <authors>
          <author>Włodarska-Kowalczuk, Maria</author>
          <author>Mazurkiewicz, Mikołaj</author>
          <author>Jankowska, Emilia</author>
          <author>Kotwicki, Lech</author>
          <author>Damrat, Mateusz</author>
          <author>Zajączkowski, Marek</author>
        </authors>
      </contributors>
      <titles>
        <title>Effects of fluvial discharges on meiobenthic and macrobenthic variability in the Vistula River prodelta (Baltic Sea)</title>
        <secondary-title>Journal of Marine Systems</secondary-title>
      </titles>
      <periodical>
        <full-title>Journal of Marine Systems</full-title>
      </periodical>
      <pages>135-146</pages>
      <volume>157</volume>
      <keywords>
        <keyword>Baltic Sea</keyword>
        <keyword>Benthos</keyword>
        <keyword>Community structure</keyword>
        <keyword>Disturbance</keyword>
        <keyword>Diversity</keyword>
        <keyword>Macrofauna</keyword>
        <keyword>Meiofauna</keyword>
        <keyword>Organic matter</keyword>
        <keyword>River prodelta</keyword>
        <keyword>Seasonality</keyword>
      </keywords>
      <dates>
        <year>2016</year>
      </dates>
      <electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.jmarsys.2015.12.009</electronic-resource-num>
      <urls>
        <pdf-urls>
          <url>internal-pdf://Włodarska-Kowalczuk et al. - 2016 - Effects of fluvial discharges on meiobenthic and macrobenthic variability in the Vistula River prode.pdf</url>
        </pdf-urls>
        <web-urls>
          <url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0924796315002341</url>
        </web-urls>
      </urls>
      <abstract>The role of environmental variability produced by river discharges in shaping the spatial and seasonal patterns of meiobenthic and macrobenthic communities was studied in the Vistula River (Baltic Sea) prodelta. Seven stations located in the delta front, the plume influence area and the distal zone of the prodelta were visited over the four seasons of 2012. Meiofauna, macrofauna, water (temperature, salinity, and suspended matter) and sediments (grain size, POC, TN, δ15N and δ13C and photosynthetic pigments) were analysed. The seasonal variations in the river discharges (with maximum flows in spring) resulted in a strong temporal variability in the studied environmental characteristics. In the benthic biota, the signals of seasonal variability, if present, were much weaker than spatial zonation. The benthic communities inhabiting the delta front where the main bulk of fluvial materials was deposited were taxonomically impoverished. The richest fauna dwelled within the plume influence area where the physical disturbance ceased and primary marine production was enhanced by river transported nutrients. In the distal zone outside the river influence, the fauna was dominated by deeper dwelling species, and the numbers of individuals and taxa decreased. Factors related to the riverine discharges (i.e., salinity, mineral suspension, POC and δ13C in the water and sediments) were identified as having high correlation with variability in the meiofaunal and macrofaunal community descriptors. Evidently, the interplay of food (i.e., the quantity and quality of organic matter) and disturbance (i.e., the deposition of river transported minerals) constraints shaped the patterns of benthic variability in the prodelta of the second largest river entering the Baltic Sea.</abstract>
      <cid>852930686038303795</cid>
      <google_cites>12</google_cites>
    </record>
  </records>
  <last_update>2024-02-23 23:27</last_update>
</xml>
